On the first of January 1901, six colonies
joined together as the Commonwealth of Australia.
Edmund Barton became the first Prime Minister.
But where to put the capital?
Sydney and Melbourne hated each other so much
that they built a whole new city in
between.
Canberra, designed by American architects Walter Burley Griffin
and Marion "Monnie" Griffin.
The new nation was a pioneer and a
paradox.
South Australian women won the right not only
to vote but to stand for parliament in
1894, a world first.
Yet one of the first laws passed began
the white Australia policy designed to keep non-European
migrants out and most aboriginal people were left
out of the vote.
Then in 1915 came Gallipoli.
Australian and New Zealand troops the Anzacs landed
in Turkey on the 25th of April.
The campaign failed and thousands died from a
population under 5 million, more than 400,000 Australians
enlisted in the First World War and over
60,000 never came home.
Every year on the 25th of April, Anzac
Day, the nation still stops to remember.